<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the treacherous procedings [sic] of the Lord of Inchequin against the Parliament of England, and some officers in their employment in the Province of Munster in Ireland. / By Collonel William Knight.</title>
            <author>Knight, William, fl. 1680-1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87814</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864981</idno>
  <idno type="VID">117214</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240907159</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing K695</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E527_18</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205669</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864981</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99864981e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87814)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117214)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 82:E527[18])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the treacherous procedings [sic] of the Lord of Inchequin against the Parliament of England, and some officers in their employment in the Province of Munster in Ireland. / By Collonel William Knight.</title>
                  <author>Knight, William, fl. 1680-1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1], 7 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1648 [i.e. 1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb: 9".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Inchiquin, Murrough O'Brien, --  Earl of, 1614-1674.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Ireland --  History --  1641-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117214:1"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION OF THE Treacherous procedings of the Lord of <hi>INCHEQUIN</hi> against the PARLIAMENT OF ENGLAND, And some Officers in their employment In the Province of <hi>Munster</hi> in <hi>IRELAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Collonel</hi> WILLIAM KNIGHT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Yeare 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117214:2"/>
            <head>A Declaration of the Treacherous proceedings of the Lord of <hi>Jnchequin</hi> against the Parliament of <hi>England, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Earing lest my Enemies by my too long silence, might take an advantage to persist in this false traducing of me, and by that means induce some of my Friends to give Credit unto the same; to stop their mouthes, and to give satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to the world of my reall and faithfull service to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> I have thought fit to publish this ensuing Declaration.</p>
            <p>Living in <hi>Ireland</hi> upon the Eruption of that horrid Rebellion (after some Services performed) for endeavouring to obstruct the Cessation then to bee made with the bloudy Irish <hi>Anno</hi> 43. for justifying the proceedings of Parliament, for writing over severall Letters to Sir <hi>William Armine,</hi> a Member of the House of Commons, of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structive proceedings of the Earle of <hi>Ormond;</hi> and his Adherents to the Parliament, and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant partie. Some of which Letters being intercepted, I was sent for to the Councell board, and from thence committed to the Castle of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and after long Imprisonment, Indicted, and try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the Kings Bench for the same, and although I were then acquitted, yet presently after by the Earle of <hi>Ormonds</hi> Order Plundered of all my Estate, my Wife turned out of of doores with that inhumanity, that it suddenly cost her her life: Presently after my acquittall, I got into <hi>England,</hi> where I no sooner came, but I entred into the Parliaments service, in which I faithfully continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon this place till 1645. then forces being raised for the service of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in the Province of <hi>Munster,</hi> I went over into the said Province, Captain of a Foot Company, where by Gods blessing upon My Endeavours, I was in <hi>August</hi> 1647 made Collonel of a Regiment of Foot and in these, and other my severall employments, continued faithfully according to the trust reposed in me; But observing a new Cessation to be made by the Lord <hi>Inchequin,</hi> and severall of his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, with the Bloody Irish in that Province, at such a time when the whole Province was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered except foure Townes, two of them not being considerable, when we could not march any wayes but the Country was as full of Cattell and Sheep, as any part of this Kingdome, with stole of Bread, and other Provisions for the Souldiery, when our Army could, and did march at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure from one end of the Province to the other, (not an Enemy daring to looke in our faces) and settled it in a constant Contribution for the maintenance of the same with Hostages delivered from the severall Counties for payment of it; By which means the Contributions were raised to so considerable a summe, that it would have plentifully maintained our Army with little help out of <hi>England</hi>: I say, observing a Cessation to be driving on at such a time when we were so abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Masters of the Field, that our Beaten. Enemies durst not appeare in the Province, when the Harvest of all our hard labours was then comming on of which we might have enjoyed a plentiful Crop I presently conceived that there was some peece of treachery to be acted against the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and Kingdome of <hi>England;</hi> and having observed that the Lord of <hi>Inchequin</hi> by private instructions from the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> affixt to his Commission, was not to carry on that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117214:2"/>War, or any Dengue upon the place, without the advice and consent of the Provincial Councell and knowing none of them to adhere to the Parliament Cause, except Col. Sir <hi>William Fenton</hi> Knight and Collonel <hi>Peregreen Banastre;</hi> About the beginning of <hi>April</hi> I repaired unto them for their advice, and told them that I had ever faithfully served the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> from the beginning of their troubles to that present. That I observed the way that the Lord of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choquin</hi> was now going, in making a Cessation with the Irish, would be Distructive to the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Religion, and the English Intrest. That my Conscience would not give me leave to steere that Course, (Besides the trust that was reposed in me) and therefore conceiv'd it my best way (in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it was out of my power to prevent his proceedings) to quit my Command, and begon for <hi>England;</hi> To which I received answers from them both (severally) that they would by no means have me do so. But to keep my Command as long as I could, for they doubted not but the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament would presently be in a Condition to look upon us, and then by my staying I might doe them good service; But if I left the place, I should but weaken their partie, and give an advantage of more strength unto their Enemies, with severall other reasons for my staying there (as those Gentlemen now upon this place, are ready to testifie) upon this I fixt my resolution according to their advice. The 22 of <hi>May</hi> following, the Cessation was concluded by the Lord of <hi>Inchequin</hi> and his Adherents with the Rebells, and then it plainly appear'd to all men (but those that were wilfully blind) that all his proceedings were Distructive to the Protestant Religion, the English intrest, and the Souldiery under his Command; First to the Protestant Cause, by giving the Irish Rebells free liberty to exercise the Romish religion, by saying Masse, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> under the very walls of all our Garrisons, when as before they were forc'd to doe it at a distance, and so privatly that the Protestant partie could take no notice of it, by tollerating their Priests, Jesuits, Fryers, and the like, to exercise their Function, and quietly enjoy their Church Livings, as by the Articles of Cessation may appear. Secondly, Distructive to the English intrest, and the Protestant partie there, by his endeavouring to turn many Protestant Families out of strong holds gained by much English bloud, and to put Irish Rebells into the same again, though long before expulst by the English sword, I will onely instance it in two, or three particulars amongst many, the strong Castle of <hi>Coolemaine,</hi> in the heart of our quarters, having a Ward kept in it by the Protestants, since the first reducing of it, and all English Tenants placed upon the Lands, yet these must presently be outed their possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Mr. <hi>Carthy Reaghe</hi> restored to the same, though the Commander in chiefe of all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells in those parts, and an active bloudy one himselfe, since the beginning of those Warres, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Plundred, burnt, and spoyled, all the English then residing in that Castle, of their Estates and livelihoods; The strong Castle of <hi>Loughart</hi> neere <hi>Malloy</hi> taken from Mr. <hi>Donnoghe,</hi> Mr. <hi>Carthy,</hi> a Grand leading Rebell, then a Prisoner in <hi>Corke,</hi> and a Garrison of English put into the same, yet by the bellowing and bleating of English sheep and cattell, Mr. <hi>Donnogh</hi> must bee set at liberty, the Garrison displaced and he restor'd to his former Possession; But his wicked Designes not stay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in these (as he conceiv'd) petty things; in the latter end of <hi>June</hi> he used extraordinary waies to patch up such a Peace with the Jrish, as that he would have restor'd them all to their former Possessions; by which means the whole City of <hi>Corke,</hi> which now consists of none but Protestants, should have been outed the said City, (though formerly by the Rebels dispoyled of all their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states) and all the Irish veceived in again; and then to have joyn'd the Army under his Command, with the Irish Rebels Army, and so to have fallen down upon Collonel <hi>Jones,</hi> and the Brittish for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, thinking thereby to have possest himselfe wholly of that Kingdome, while the divisions were so high in this, and so according to his often expressions, have made that Kingdome independent to <hi>England,</hi> and possibly he might have thoughts to be King of <hi>Munster,</hi> as he hath been pleased seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall times of late to affirme his Ancestors were. Thirdly, distructive to the Souldiery by giving a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way two Counties, <hi>Limrick</hi> and <hi>Tipperong</hi> (upon the Cessation) which wee had conquer'd by
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117214:3"/>the Sword, except the foresaid Towns, for the maintenance of the Irish Army under the command of the Lord <hi>Taffe,</hi> which two Counties did afford us about 4000 pounds <hi>per mensem,</hi> towards the payment of our Army: with these and the like abominable practises, because I could not Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply without the highest Breach of trust both with God and man, nor stay upon the place to see them acted with a safe Conscience, and finding severall, of the best affected Officers to the Parliament, to perceive their former error, and enveigh much against these his unjust procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings (and that most of the Protestant party; were disaffected with the same: who had observed many of his false and pernicious oathes to them made, and never kept, as one amongst the rest at <hi>Mallow,</hi> when calling all his Officers, together then with him, Told them that he heard there was a disaffected party in the Army, that used all the endeavours they could, to possesse the Army, that he intended to joyn them with the Irish Forces and so endeavoured to beget an ill opinion of him and his proceedings amongst the said Officers and his Army, and after many oathes, and execrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by him made to the contrary dismist them; yet within two dayes after, sent his Potent to seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Regiments, to rise and march into <hi>Thomond</hi> to Lieutenant Generall <hi>Purcell,</hi> (the L. <hi>Taffes</hi> Lieut. General) and to joyn with his Forces against Sir <hi>Charles Coote,</hi> and from time to time, to obey all such orders as they should receive from <hi>Purcell,</hi> or in his absence from his Brother <hi>Christopher Bryen,</hi> one that we had taken Prisoner long before at the fight of <hi>Ahecooty,</hi> and never exchang'd or ransom'd, this perfidiousnes of his (amongst many others) being observ'd, &amp; hated by the better par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I thought it then a fit time to step in and confer with some Officers and Townsmen of most note, and integrity, by laying before them the great danger they were fallen into, as also prescribing a remedy, how the Parliaments intrest might yet be preserved with their safeties, all which I concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be very Cordiall to act any thing with me for the English good; the L. of <hi>Inchequin</hi> being then out of Town, came home the next day: the morning following he sent for me, where I soone perceiv'd all the businesse was discovered unto him, I perceiving it was no time time to go back by denying what I intended to have acted after some discourse 'twixt him and my selfe, (before severall Officers) told him that I much wondred at that course he now steer'd in declining the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>England,</hi> conceiving there could be little security to him by taking that course he now did, in regard the King could not cordially love him, because he had formerly deserted him; The Queen he knew could not choose but hate him, for those loose reports, he frequently, and publikly used of her; For the Marquis of <hi>Ormond</hi> into whose hand he was now giving all the Power hee had let him but well weigh the late difference that was betwixt them, and he might easily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude from thence that the Marquis of <hi>Ormond</hi> playd but his former game, and that being once playd he might expect onely to have the honour, as to be last Cashier'd out of the Army, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore desir'd him to desist from these proceedings, which would speak him fickle to all the world, in now betraying the trust reposed in him by the Parliament; But this discourse not affecting him, hee told me he would break the neck of the Jndependent partie, and without any more words, I was forthwith (being the ninth of <hi>July</hi>) committed to my quarters, with a guard of Musquettiers upon me, presently after J was Articled against at a Court Martiall, and two dayes before J was to bee tryed, he calling severall of his Officers together, told them amongst other things, there could bee no safety for them and the Army, unlesse they took me out of the way; upon the seventeenth of <hi>August</hi> I came to my tryall upon the said Articles, the Copies of which proceedings fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
            <div type="document">
               <head>Articles exhibited at a Court Martiall held at <hi>Corck</hi> against Collonel <hi>William Knight,</hi> by <hi>Joshua Boyle</hi> Esquire Judge Advocate, as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IMprimis, <hi>It is objected, Articled and alleaged against him the said Collonel</hi> William Knight, <hi>that contrary to his duty, contrary to the Laws, Orders, and Customes Military, he the said Collonel</hi> William Knight <hi>hath most wickedly and maliciously practised, and endeavoured to sow sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117214:3"/>and breed mutiny in the Army, and to raise and foment division, and faction amonst the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, and Commanders thereof against the Right Honourable the Lord President of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, and Generall of the said Army, and in pursuance of such his wicked designs, in the month of</hi> June <hi>last, or in this present month of</hi> July <hi>in presence of divers Officers, and other persons (to the end to draw them into the same practice with himselfe) hath spoken and uttered seditious words and language tending to breed mutiny in the said Army, and distrust of the Generall aforesaid, in his under takings and designs for the publique service, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Item, <hi>It is objected, Articled and alleaged that he the said Collonel</hi> William Knight <hi>for the furtherance of that his wicked purpose, and for the causing of mutiny in the Army hath lately la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to seduce many of the chiefe Officers thereof, and to perswade them,</hi> (<hi>and more particularly Collonel</hi> Richard Townsend) <hi>that there is a designe intended against them, for their Cashierements from their severall commands, and that they might be induced to practice with him, and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices, in the same combination, hath assured them that a List of the names of twelve Officers of quality in the said Army (whereof he affirmed the said Collonel</hi> Townsend <hi>to be one) was sent from hence into</hi> France <hi>to the Marquesse of</hi> Ormond, <hi>as Officers not sit to be trusted, in order to the Kings affaires, with a List of as many Cavalliers to succeed in their places, intending thereby to possesse the Members of the said Army with an apprehension of much danger, in his said Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships arrivall in this Province, that so they might combine with the best of their indeavours, to obstruct the same, and to beget an opinion among the said Officers, that there is a Complotment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Lord President, Generall of this Army, and the said Marquesse of</hi> Ormond, <hi>for the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shiering of all Officers of quality who have served under the Parliament; and by this means to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get a disopinion of his Lordships proceedings to raise a distrust of his Generall, and cause breach of unity and disturbance in the Army.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Item, <hi>It is objected, Articled and alleaged that he the said Collonel</hi> William Knight, <hi>for the better accomplishing of this his wicked designe, hath advised, and endeavoured to perswade many of the principall Officers of the said Army, that there can be no security for them (who have served the Parliament) in this Province, except they could gaine into their hands the Town and Fort of</hi> Kinsale <hi>to be put under the Command of such a Parliamenteeras they should approve of, by which said undue practice, he the said Coll.</hi> Knight <hi>designed to necessirate his Lordship, either to comply with his foresaid demands by yeilding the said Towne and Fort, By attaining whereunto he insinuated they might be at liberty to receive support &amp; Conditions from the Independent party by Sea, and with more security proceed to further resolutions, or else by denying them to ncrease that Jealousie and destrust of his Lordship to a higher flame, which by his many soule suggestions he had kindled within them, and the said Collonel</hi> William Knight <hi>in pursuance of his wicked designes, for deviding and engaging the said Armies into factions and parties one against another, and more particularly to ingage a party for the Independent faction, hath laboured to perswade divers Officers of the said Army, that there was no such thing as the Princes comming into</hi> England, <hi>and that he was a dull man and not to be drawn into any action of consequence, and that all things were in a quiet, and peaceable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion under the Independent power, and that the Lord of</hi> Broghall <hi>would be imployed with a Fleet of men and mony to be tendred unto us here, But if resused would be dispatcht for</hi> Dublin, <hi>By which practises, and endeavours to divide the said Army, nothing could be more palpably designed then the utter ruine and subversion of the same, unlesse it could be brought to subjection to the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent power in</hi> England, <hi>by which means the English interest in this Kingdome must have been ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly lost and extinguished.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Item, <hi>It is objected, Articled and alleaged that he the said Collonel</hi> William Knight, <hi>for the speedy perfecting of that and other his malitious intents, in absence of his said Lordship then in the Country did dispatch away Letters, to several Officers of the said Army for their speedy repaire to the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117214:4"/>towne of</hi> Corck, <hi>thinking in that opportunity of time, with more facility to seduce, and perswade them to joyne with him, to have something in a readinesse to act against his Lordships returne, which can be no other thing then the apprehending and securing of his Lordships Person, upon his just refusall of his unjust demands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Item, <hi>It is objected Articled and alleaged, that he the said Collonel</hi> William Knight <hi>by his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and discourse hath laboured to foment differences, betwixt his Majesty, and the Presbiterian party, thereby designing to raise discord in the said Army, and to gaine a greater party to adhere unto him in his aforesaid practises, all which have tended very much to the disadvantage of the Protestant party, and prejudice of the publique service,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <head>The relation of Lieutenant Collonel <hi>Edward Doyley</hi> Jurat 17 <hi>August</hi> 1648.</head>
               <p>IN the month of <hi>July</hi> last, Collonel <hi>William Knight</hi> and this deponent walking in <hi>Cork</hi>-streets, streets, Collonel <hi>Knight</hi> said, how, now <hi>Dorley,</hi> doe you intend to stand to your principles, To which this deponent answered yes, And if any man can convince me, I doe not in the way I now goe, I will decline it to morrow, then Collonel <hi>Knight</hi> replyed I wish you may. But how can that be when they say my Lord of <hi>Ormond</hi> is comming over, To which this Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent answered for his comming over I am well satisfied. I know upon what account he comes here <hi>(viz.)</hi> By Directions, and approbation of the Presbiterian party in <hi>England,</hi> and the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> To which, Collonel <hi>Knight</hi> said well, well, be not deceived, that cannot be, you understand your selfe, and have served the Parliament, he comes over here Lord Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and must command all, and then what will become of you and me, and all that have served the Parliament, and their Interest, to which this Deponent said I feare him not, he can do us no harme so long as my Lord stands to us, which I am confident he will, he having made so many professions to us, and his Interest being involued with ours; Then said Collonel <hi>Knight</hi> that's true, But I can assure you the Marquesse of <hi>Ormond</hi> is one of the greatest head pieces in the three Kingdomes, and may over-reach him, and you, come, Come I tell you there came lately one from <hi>France</hi> who saw a list of twelve (names in my Lord of <hi>Ormonds</hi> study) of Officers here that served the Parliament, that were sent from hence, and to be Cashiered at his comming over, as men not fit to be trusted, To which this Deponent said are you sure of that, then Collonel <hi>Knight</hi> said my life for the truth of it, Come <hi>Doyley</hi> we are in a mist, I could tell you many things if as Agent, you would not speake of them, To which this Deponent said, Collonel <hi>Knight</hi> trust me not with what you would not have knowne, for I cannot promise you, well said Collonel <hi>Knight</hi> why should not my Lord give us the Towne and Fort of <hi>Kinesale</hi> for our security. To which this Deponent answered, I doubt not but he will, if it can be made appeare to him, wee are in any danger by my Lord of <hi>Ormonds</hi> comming, But how can wee doe amisse, when my Lord is true to us, and most of the Souldiery inclined to the Parliament, then said Collonel <hi>Knight</hi> what if my Lord of <hi>Ormond</hi> should bring the Irish Armies upon us, To which this Deponent said sure Collonel <hi>Knight</hi> you cannot but know, though my Lord of <hi>Ormond</hi> be a Royalist, he is true to the Intrest, and Crowne of <hi>England,</hi> To which Collonel <hi>Knight</hi> said you know him not so well as I doe, I wish still you be not deceived, all that you heare is not so, wee have great talkes of the Prince, and Armies in <hi>England,</hi> there is no such matter as I can heare, for the Prince tis true he is much urged to goe by a great Company of gallants that are with him. But he is a dull man and cannot be perswaded to goe, if we had a Garrison wee were secure, To which this Deponent said who can we trust that will not comply with the Shipping to make his owne peace, To which Collonel <hi>Knight</hi> said the rest must bee engaged to my Lord for him; then said this Deponent I will move any thing with others to my Lord; But I will have nothing to doe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hand, Then said Collonel <hi>Knight</hi> my Lord is a gallant man, I wish he be not deceived, hee
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117214:4"/>he shall have only the honour to be Cashiered last, then said this Deponent come, we will go to Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Townsend</hi> and talke of these things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="court_order">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Ordered.</hi> 17 <hi>August</hi> 1648. At a Court of War.</head>
                           <p>Whereas it evidently appeared unto this Court as well by the Examinations against Collonel <hi>William Knight,</hi> as by his own Confession, that he the said Collonel had uttered divers words, unto Lieutenant Collonel <hi>Edward Doyley,</hi> and Collonel <hi>Richard-Townsend,</hi> which were by the Court adjudged to raise mutiny and faction in the Army; the Court therefore after long debate had of the whole matter, did unanimously vote and declare, that the said Collonell <hi>William Knight</hi> should be Cashiered from his Regiment, and bee committed close Prisoner during the pleasure of the Right Honourable the Lord President, and sentence accordingly was given.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="petition">
                           <head>The Petition of Collonel <hi>William Knight:</hi> To the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable the Lord President of <hi>Mnnster.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>SHeweth, that your Petitioner, at a Martiall Court was Cashiered from his Regiment, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisoned during your Lordships pleasure, that for these three yeares he hath served your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship according to the trust reposed in him, he came over here to serve your Lordship under the Parliament of</hi> England, <hi>and upon no other account, your Supplicants request is, that he may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>least of his imprisonment, and have your Lordships passe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <dateline>
                                 <date>12. Octob. 1648.</date>
                              </dateline>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                        <div type="response">
                           <p>The Petitioner having abused the Liberty and favour already afforded him, by entring into new Combinations and fresh practises, I may not give any eare or Concession to his present request.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>INCHIQUIN.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>After this I was imprisoned severall months, and then Lieutenant Collonel <hi>Beecher,</hi> was sent from the Parliament with the Lord of <hi>Inchiquins</hi> Son, to setch of all Prisoners, that suffered for them upon that place, but such was the malice of the Lord of <hi>Inchiquin</hi> to me, that rather then I should be Exchanged upon that account he commands Lieutenant Collonel <hi>Beechar</hi> to depart the harbour, and take his Son back for <hi>England</hi> I then being excluded the Exchange was foret (with all the means I could make for the quitting of my self) to deposit 100 l. in Collonel <hi>Ster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings</hi> hand to procure Sir <hi>Arthur Blany</hi> Knight, or Lieutenant Collonel <hi>Crafford</hi> for my Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, or within six months to render my selfe a Prisoner againe, other wayes to forfeit the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid 100 l. as appears by my parole. Notwitstanding all these my sufferings, malice having fild the mouths of some of my enemies, who dare but barke at a distance, yet by insinnuation more then by any desert, are crept into the bosomes of some gallant and Religious Gentlemen, and with their smooth, yet false speeches, indeavour to cast an odium upon me, that I have ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved against the Parliament, and this Army, and only suffered out of some self ends of my owne, By which false aspersions, two much credit being given unto them by some, who should have two eares to heare before one tongue to censure, all my just applications either to the Parliament, or Army for some reparations for these my great sufferings, and for my Arrears so dearly earned with the price of my bloud, though invited by an Ordinance of Parliament, are obstructed and blasted before I can bring them to any perfection so as to stop the mouth of malice and to undeceive all good Christians, I am forced with an unwilling, willingnesse to put my self in Print, and by this my Declaration to manifest to the world, the innocency and integrity of my heart and actions, desiring all that shall read the same seriously to consider what I have said and then judge.</p>
               <p>As likewise the time when I appeared for the Parliament, being the beginning of <hi>Iuly</hi> last, when the Cavalleers had <hi>Colchester,</hi> when <hi>Langhorne</hi> was up in <hi>Wales,</hi> when the rising was in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117214:5"/>
                  <hi>Kent,</hi> and severall other parts of the Kingdome, when the Scots were ready to invade <hi>England</hi> on the one side, and the revolted Ships on the other, when the Lord of <hi>Inchiquin,</hi> and his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates thought they had been ready to have devoured Collonel <hi>Iones,</hi> and the Brittish for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which undoubtedly they had attempted had not God (by me his weake instrument) inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed at that time, which bred such a destraction amongst his Officers, that it was impossible for him to carry on that designe or to knit them together to this day; as at this day it is most e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident when it was expected, and here below decreed, that the Parliament and Army should have been swallowed up in a moment, and an end put to both their beings. I say to step out at such a time, (when I might have been courted to have sitten down with so great a Command, as I then had) let the world judge what selfe-end. I could then have; But if the time were such when Gods glory, and the publique welfare lay at stake, and that I engag'd for no other end then the endeavouring to the utmost of my power to preserve them both, and to keep a good Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence both before God and man; Then God in his good time, (mangre the malice of my enemies) will cause my innocency to breake forth as the Sun at noon-day, yet in case he will not (let them know) I am resolv'd to wait his good pleasure with patience, and lay forth my selfe to the utmost of my power, when I shall be thereunto called, for the good of his Church, and people, though never so much discountenanced by man for the present, were I conscious of the least breach of trust in my publique mployment: I would judge my self, by laying my hand upon my mouth, for some particular failings twixt me and other private men: Far be it from me to justifie my selfe, <hi>humanum est errari;</hi> But for my service to the Publique, I must professe before God and man, that I have faithfully served the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> since the first infancy of their troubles, according (o the trust reposed in me and this I am confident will be enough to satisfie good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, and honest men; for others it is too much, being assured that nothing will satisfie them. To conclude, for the Lord of <hi>Inchiquin,</hi> and his Machivilian tricks, with the very genius of the <hi>Hocus Pocus,</hi> and how that, under seeming sanctity, and the Cloak of Religion, he hath deceived both King, Parliament, and Souldiery; his ayme tending to no other end, then the destruction of the Protestant Religion, and party, and the annihilating of the English interest in that Kingdome. All which I will at large fully and faithfully publish to the view of the world, that posterity may be acquainted with his treachery, which is more fit for a Volume then a Manifesto.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>